[Music]
so and we are live
good evening good day everyone and
welcome to episode 11
of the ask abijit show it's great to be
back with you again
so before i begin i would like to thank
you all i would like to thank you for
your viewership and for all the comments
and all the questions that you're asking
it's uh
you have reposed a lot of trust in me so
i am very very grateful to
each and every one every one of you from
the bottom of my heart so
thank you everyone once again now some
people have asked
have been asking how do you ask
questions on this channel
so the answer is very simple ask your
questions in the form of comments on any
of my videos
and use this hashtag this hashtag down
here
ask abidjit in your questions because
that is what's going to help me find
those
questions and many of you have
asked how do you have been requesting me
to make short clips of
my various uh long videos so i have been
doing that i have created a new channel
called ask
called a widget chapter clips just uh
search for abhijit chavda clips
on youtube and the link for this
new channel is also in the description
of this video and every other video
so you'll be able to find that short
clips channel there
i am putting individual answers to
questions in that channel
and and eventually all of the
interesting and important questions will
be
put on that channel in the form of short
clips
so today is a live q a session so i have
been
recently focusing on the questions
you're asking in comments because i want
to
basically find the best of your
questions and i want to create
content that is valuable to all of you
for a very long time
it should be valuable to you even 10 20
years down the line
so that is the reason why i'm picking
and choosing questions the best
questions
so that it provides you value in the
long run but i know that you guys
also want interaction live live chat so
once a week we're gonna have this
live q a session which will be only
based on live
questions which you ask me so this is a
60 minute session and the 60 minutes
starts
now so let me find some good questions
and first of all
uh thank you again to all of you all of
you who have been contributing super
chats
and super stickers i have not been
focusing much on that but i am very
grateful
for that contribution i really
appreciate it thank you
so let's begin now we have lots of
questions
lots of questions where do i begin let
me see
let me find okay let us start with this
question what happens if beetlejuice
explodes
so beetlejuice is a red supergiant star
let's located about 700 light years
from where we are from our solar system
which means that if we shine a beam of
light at that star
it will take that light 700 years to
reach there and it also means that what
we are seeing from that star right now
is what actually happened there 700
years ago
so this is a red super giant star it's
about 700 times the diameter of the sun
and it's about 10 million or so years
old
and it is in the last stages of its
lifespan
it is a star that that is known to
brighten and dim erratically
sporadically
and it is expected to go supernova soon
which means it will explode soon now
when will this happen it could happen
tomorrow it could happen next week or it
could happen sometime in the next
100 000 years 1 lakh years so when this
star explodes first of all it is not a
threat to us
a star would need to go supernova some
somewhere in the
in the vicinity in the vicinity of 50 or
so light years
for it to pose a possible threat to the
solar system and to us
living on this planet this star when it
explodes it is not going to be a threat
to us but it's going to uh give a give a
very interest very spectacular light
show so it will
shine with the intensity of almost
the moon or maybe half the moon and when
we see the moon in the sky it's
it's this big right but this star when
it explodes all that light will come
from a single point because it's so far
away
so it's going to be a very bright point
in the sky a very
luminous point it's gonna be visible in
the daytime for several months
and it will be visible in the night sky
for like two or three years perhaps
so that's what's going to happen and it
is situated in the orion
constellation so after it goes supernova
and it dies that star will vanish from
there
so that's what happens when this star
explodes
99 of the energy of the supernova
explosion will be
in the form of neutrinos which are
invisible these are weakly interacting
particles
so when this nucle this nutrient of wave
reaches us we'll be able to study
uh the well some of the physics and
dynamics of the supernova explosion
but for all of us it's going to be a
very interesting show
show in the sky very beautiful light
show
so that's what happens when it explodes
it will have explode sometime in the
next
one lakh years let me take another
question
can you explain the history of the
banjara people and do the banjaras have
an
early link with the indus valley
civilization so the banjara people
are a nomadic people who live
within india who travel within india
mostly in the
rajasthan gujarat region northern india
western india region
and we don't know exactly when these
people became
they became nomadic traditionally
if you look at the antique antiquity of
india the long history of india we did
not have nomadic people
so something happened at some point in
time some historical event
that uh rendered these people destitute
and homeless
and uh reduced to wandering
and it's strange that even after
independence when we are when we have
our own form of government etc
these people are still homeless and
destitute and still nomadic
so we don't know exactly the origins of
how they became
nomadic how they're forced to adopt a
nomadic lifestyle
this has not been studied by historians
what i believe is during the foreign
invasions the turkic invasions
many people were uprooted their life
lives were destroyed etc
and especially those who resisted the
invaders and occupiers
so maybe it is those these banjaras are
possibly the descendants of those
people who resisted and who were
basically expelled
from their their native uh ancestral
homelands and they were forced to go
into exile some people were
were forced to go into exile in forests
otherwise they would be killed
especially people who fought who fought
back and resisted
so maybe it became a tradition over time
because they had to
spend centuries in hiding in forests and
hills
and eventually they were able to come
out in the open but they don't have any
homes anymore
they have lost their homeland and their
hometowns so maybe that is the origin
of the banjalas it's a very interesting
piece of history and it is something
that needs to be rectified
these people need to be rehabilitated do
they have any link with the indus valley
civilization
yes we all have links with the indus
valley or harappan
era of india's civilization it is not
a separate civilization it is one of the
specific
eras in the timeline of indian history
and india's civilization
so every one of us has genetic
and cultural linkages from
the harappan era of our civilization our
culture which we practice today with
hinduism buddhism and all the various
different forms of dharmic
culture they are all very much attested
in the various artifacts we have
discovered all across the place in the
so called harappan region indus valley
region
so yes we are directly linked to that
civilization we are descendants
of that phase of our civilization we
have genetic ties and cultural ties and
all in civilizational ties
with the indus valley civilization and
so do the banjara people
good question good question
sujit asks if the universe is expanding
why is andromeda galaxy coming towards
us
see the expansion of the universe
happens at the very largest
scales it happens because what we
believe is some kind of
force or energy that permeates space
time
we call it dark energy because we don't
know what it is so this is something
that's
very very dilute it's present it is
about
its concentration is very low and
because of that
the because of the low concentration of
this particular force or energy
that's why at the local scales gravity
is able to overpower it
and gravity is able to bring things
closer so
dark energy is its effect is visible
at the larger scales at the scale of
galaxy super clusters
and and beyond that so that's why we
find that far away galaxy clusters and
supervisors are receding from us
and we can see that because of the red
shift so the spectral lines
of these these galaxies and stars
galaxies mostly and super clusters of
galaxies when we analyze the spectral
lines
we find that the spectral lines are red
shifted they are shifted towards the red
end of the spec spectrum which indicates
that they are moving away from us and we
are able to find that the
expansion this recession of other
celestial
objects is actually accelerating so
that's why it happens on the largest
scales of the universe
but on local scales it doesn't it is not
able to overpower gravity
at the local scales gravity overpowers
dark energy that is why andromeda and
the earth and the and the milky way are
coming towards each other and they will
eventually
collide and merge some five billion or
so years
in the future
what's my answer to the leftist people
who claim there was no idea of india
before the british arrived on india's
soil
for them all the princely states were
countries in the subcontinent
let's take a look at the history of the
united kingdom let's go back a thousand
years
you had the kingdom of mercia
you had the kingdom of northumbria you
had wessex you had
essex you had sussex you had whales you
had the northern lands
these were all independent kingdoms they
fought fiercely and
bitterly amongst each other and
therefore we can use the same argument
to claim that the united kingdom
is not a legitimate country it is it was
just a bunch of
separate disparate fragmented kingdoms
who fought amongst each other and who
had a great deal of
ancient enmities with each other so the
same
idea can be applied everywhere else you
can apply it to germany
rhineland saxony and what not you can
apply to every
present day country so this is
an ideology that seeks to break up india
to fragment india
right these people they are essentially
on the payroll
of external forces uh we can
i think i'm sure we can all guess what
those external forces are
and that's why they keep pushing this
narrative that india was never a nation
india was never a cohesive whole and
that
is what is peddled in our
academic system our academic system is
a means of social engineering it is a
means of
inculcating these these incorrect and
false
ideas in the minds of the future
generations and even most of us most of
us have grown up
believing in this so-called idea of
india india is
not an idea india is a civilization
it is the most ancient civilization
known to humankind
and it is the oldest surviving
civilization
on the planet so that is what india is
and and these people they they
essentially are
basically like i said trying to divide
and fragment india
so all we need to do is to learn the
true history of our country it's one
culture
and one civilization that's the that's
the basic definition of a civilization
it is one overarching cultural and
civilizational umbrella
it has one overarching culture one
overarching civilizational language
and one single means of one single
methodology
of governance all the institutions are
steeped
and based in the indigenous culture they
don't have foreign laws
so until 1947 india was a proper
civilization
now because of our foreign
constitutional laws we are struggling
with that and that's why these
ideas are brought in to make a struggle
further and to fragment us
further so it is time it's it's long
been time to reform the education system
and to get rid of this
these these these divisive
and patently false ideas so that's what
i
have to say about this in very brief
what's my idea about the big bang theory
well it's a theory it's not a hypothesis
it's been
tested so when you uh
when you encounter a physical phenomenon
in the universe you make a hypothesis
which means you make an educated guess
about what is the cause of that
and then you test it you test it with
observational evidence and other means
and then if your hypothesis doesn't
pass the test that you discard the
hypothesis and you bring in a new
hypothesis a better improved hypothesis
and then you again see if it matches if
the predictions of this hypothesis
they match with the observed evidence or
not and if it does match then it becomes
no longer a hypothesis it becomes
a working theory or model of that
phenomenon so
that is the big bang theory it's a
working model it's a theory
of the uh of the origin and the
evolution
of the universe it has been tested
extensively
thus far from the tests that we have
done from the best
test data that we have the best
instruments that we have the big bang
is the best available theory of the
origin
and evolution of the universe so that is
the big bang theory it is the best model
and the best theory
that we have thus far it has been tested
extensively
and thus far it has passed
the test there are many gaping holes
still in our standard model in the big
bang theory
and in various aspects of physical
cosmology astrophysics and much more
there are enormous gaps in our knowledge
but this is thus far the best model that
we have
and whatever prediction it does make
they have been
thus far tested to be and proven to be
correct
with the best instrumentation and
all of that that we have
okay let me
zuman we thank you for sharing your
immense knowledge of years of knowledge
we are thankful thank you so much suman
thank you very much i appreciate your
kind words thank you
okay if a situation comes off a
double-fronted war between pakistan and
china what is india's current position
to defend
herself and potentially gaining any land
occupied by the two nations
well i do not foresee a hot war between
india and china
pakistan is not a threat for us we are
overwhelmingly
more powerful than china than pakistan
china
is definitely a threat overall if you
look at its military capabilities
as of today they are superior to ours
they have more it's all about
numbers they have more aircraft fighter
aircraft
they have more tanks they have more
missiles they have
a much much larger navy their navy is
now even larger than the u.s navy
so if you look at the numbers china is
much more powerful than us
the good thing is that china is occupied
on the eastern and other regions
because of various other threats and
india doesn't really pose
a territorial threat to china because
india has never attempted to retake
or free tibet so china doesn't see india
as a threat
china uses pakistan as a proxy to keep
india destabilized and it's worked very
successfully thus far
can india in the future gain any land
occupied by the two nations
well as of now it is difficult to take
back
aksai chin from the chinese or to free
tibet from the chinese because china
has a very stable and powerful
government and powerful military
in the future it could be possible if
the chinese communist party
goes out of power now how would that
happen that would happen
if they would suffer a military defeat
somewhere and they would lose their
prestige and position in the
eyes of the common people this has
happened over and over and over again
in chinese history over the past 2000
years of chinese history it's called
dynastic cycles you have a powerful
dynasty all
powerful which suddenly crumbles because
of some
some eventuality that was not foreseen
so
that is the possible way in which china
could
in which the chinese communist party
could go out of power if it
makes some foolhardy if it takes some
foolhardy
uh ill thought out steps and loses
a military engagement galwan was a was a
warning sign for them
so the thing is see the chinese i don't
believe they will ever try to engage in
a
full-scale war with india they have much
better ways of destabilizing
india and keeping india down i mean look
at what's happened since
2010 2020 china's economy has grown by
leaps and bounds in this past
year and a half and india's economy has
ground to a crawl
right india's tourism sector is dead
india's hospitality hospitality sector
is dead
india's manufacturing is nowhere india's
trade
is nowhere india's people are are hidden
in their houses the whole country has
gone to
ground to a stop india's space program
is is frozen
chandrayaan was supposed to be launched
last year the
ghanaian the human spaceflight program
was supposed to happen this time next
year
and next next year as well well nothing
is happening
so china has achieved all of this
without ever resorting to war
i mean this is a better outcome than
going to war so china i do not think
we'll ever want to go
want to risk a war with india a
nuclear-powered nation that's always a
risk
so china has lots of other means of
keeping india down and these are
more powerful means so that is the
chinese game plan use all these
different
use war by other means lawfare and other
things right
so and biological warfare cyber warfare
other forms of warfare there are many
other
forms of warfare that don't cross the
threshold of kinetic warfare
and those are more advantages and china
has
the chinese are patient this is a
hundred year marathon for them
so that is the thing i don't see any
eventuality of a double-fronted war with
china and pakistan
if it does happen we always have the
last option which is nuclear weapons we
can tell them back off or else
so i think india in the in the in
as far as hot war goes is pretty much
safe
it is the other non-lethal non
kinetic warfare that is the real threat
to india it's an indus insidious threat
and we don't even see it
right so that is the real problem that
is the real threat to india
let me find some more questions
amit asks left i think i answered this
question
yeah yeah thank you thank you for this
question thank you i asked i answered
this
all right some more questions
uh okay uh what are my thoughts on the
sudden rise of
soft power of asian giants like korea
and japan will the same will the quest
for the same ignite interest of the
government of india towards our history
you know india is a dormant cultural
historical and civilizational superpower
it can become the next
tourism superpower in the next five to
ten years if india
invests in the infrastructure of tourism
india has india is basically the
homeland of
every buddhist person on this planet
that is most of east asia isn't it and
even the people who practice
let's say the people of indonesia even
though the practice of foreign religion
nowadays
they practice islam nowadays most of
them many of them
and still they still feel this this
the sentiment that india is the
ancestral homeland because the
indonesians they many of them
have some indian ancestry as well so
india has a great deal of potential now
look at
powers like korea and japan these are
not military powers but these are
economic powers
korea was destroyed in the korean war in
the 1950s
and after that it came back it developed
its economy
right it uh tightened up its governance
and in just a few decades it's become
a first world country with the highest
standards of living
and when a nation becomes prosperous
that's when
culture flourishes you can't have
culture
of flourishing without when your nation
is poor
right people don't have the time to
enjoy culture when they're struggling to
make
make ends meet and the same goes for
japan japan was destroyed devastated
in world war ii and it rebuilt itself
from scratch
and became an economic superpower until
the 1990s
after that there's been a period of
stagnation uh
and yet japan is a very powerful economy
it is a force to be reckoned with
it has the highest uh technological
advancement of almost any nation in the
world
and yet it is so much in tune and in
touch with its ancestral culture
and that is the thing about japan it
embraces modernity
while being a very traditional nation
it's a brilliant combination
and that's why japan is so attractive to
so many people it is so modernistic so
futuristic
and yet so traditional that is the the
usp of japan so we can learn a great
deal from japan
and from korea the number one thing we
have to learn is we need to boost our
economy we need to bring our per capita
gdp
high high we need to increase that our
per capita gdp
is currently the same as most nations in
africa
right if you if you divide the total gdp
of india
by the population the number that comes
out is abysmal it's
terrible so we need to boost our overall
gdp which will
boost our per capita gdp which means
that we will have higher standards of
living
so that's what india needs to do first
of all only when the living standards
are high
will culture start to flourish 20 years
ago there was no sport in india i mean
india was very poor at sports
and yet now that the nation is becoming
slower slowly
more more prosperous you can see more
and more sports people emerging
and getting medals on global stages
because when you have more prosperity
you can
spend time playing sports and doing
culture so that's the thing
india needs to focus a great deal on its
economy india needs to bring everyone
out of poverty
and you cannot do this at the expense of
military strength
because there's no point being a
economically strong nation when your
military is weak which means that
anybody can come and steal your money
so these are the things that india needs
to focus on and if india does focus on
this
then culture will revive on its own
cultural uh
you will have a cultural renaissance and
with the cultural renaissance you will
have a
resurgence in interest in india india
has the most powerful and influential
culture of the ancient world
right and with that will
come a resurgence in interest in our
history
so the main thing is to rebuild our
economy
to to uplift the people to give them
higher and higher standards of living
the kind of standards of living we used
to have for millennia for thousands of
years
so that's what we need to focus on while
not neglecting the military strength
people said that we don't have money for
military we need to spend it on the
uh upliftment of people my point is very
simple
if you uplift the people and build a
strong economy
people is a stronger power can always
come and steal your money or destroy
your economy
you need to invest in military as well
so that you can protect everything that
you're building
so that's my answer to this very good
question
shashwat asks some say buddha did kill
many people even after bill becoming
buddha is it true
no i've never heard of such a such a
such a story
uh the buddha is not known or recorded
to have killed anybody
during his lifetime as far as we know
and recorded in the records that we have
about him
so no i don't know where you heard this
from but i would definitely
say it is not it is not the case
[Music]
okay some more questions
uh please give me a minute let me find
some questions
so lara thomas asks me why don't we have
as much written information from before
and during the antiquity period of india
such as the guptas compared to the roman
empire
the reason is very simple we had
this immense education system
which started from the very grassroots
and went all the way up we had
small temples that served as schools in
every
locality in every town and village when
you had larger temples
then you had great temples and you had
universities the great universities
these were all educational
institutions we also had the mahaviharas
and much more
so we had an enormous network of
educational institutions in this country
all of that was destroyed during the
turkic invasions of india
they sought out and destroyed our
universities and their immense libraries
you had so many great great universities
and like nalanda
taksha sheila telhara vikram sheela
udantapuri
sharda pete and so many that we have
whose existence we don't even know of
today because
those are all in ruins and those ruins
are not explored at all
so these great universities
where the home of homes of the greatest
minds
of antiquity from all over the world
people used to come from all over the
world from china from greece
from scitia and many other places and
these
universities had immense libraries that
contained
the records of our ancestors of our
history of our sciences of our
philosophies
of pharmacology mathematics astronomy
and what not
and these records went back thousands of
years thousands of years
when the greeks came to india during
chandragupta's time they
they attested to the fact that india's
calendar at that time
went back to 6600 or so bce
and it had the entire lineages of
thousands and thousands of kings
and all of this all of this all of these
universities
all of these libraries and all of those
historical records were destroyed during
the turkic invasions every library was
burned
uh the library at naranda is known to
have burned for several months
so you can imagine how many records we
lost we lost all
of the records of our ancient history
and that's why all we are left with
is some rudimentary fragmentary
fragmentary orally transmitted
uh recollections of our history which
our ancestors after the turkic invasions
passed on from from generation to
generation orally because that was all
they had left
and after the british came to india they
said that all of your older oral
histories are myths
and then they proceeded to write their
own british version of india's history
and that is what our education system
teaches us today which is a very
shameful thing
so that is why there is so little
written
information about our antiquity
as compared to other countries like
greece or rome all we know today is what
we are able to piece back from
archaeological evidence and some texts
that we
may discover lying somewhere gathering
dust somewhere
there are still millions of indian texts
that have escaped destruction
those are all gathering dust and those
are all slowly getting
decomposed because the government of
india is paying no attention to that
the asi is paying our attention so that
is the state we are it
and to answer your question i think that
answers your question because everything
was destroyed during the turkic
invasions that's why we have so little
records of our ancient history
okay let me find some more questions
that's a good question by the way
okay vivek sinha thank you i read in an
article that kiljee did not
resist the mongols to save india's
culture and civilization he did
it to save himself but that is true for
even shivaji
rana p or lakshmi by thought
okay so first of all there is this
wonderful misconception that maha that
alladin khilji defeated chingish khan
several times
so that is not the case uh chinggis khan
died
at least a few decades before this guy
khilji was born
and what khilji did was he repulsed some
half-hearted mongol invasions
which were not from the main mongol
empire there were some
half-hearted incursions into india by
some
by some raiding parties or some
reconnaissance groups
those were not full-fledged invasions of
india and like you said he was not doing
anything for india's history and culture
or civilization he was doing it to
safeguard the empire he had amassed for
himself
the kingdom the delay sultanate it was
all under him it was indian territory
that he
was occupying that he was extracting
from and
enriching himself from so that was what
he was trying to protect he was trying
to protect his investment
he was trying to protect the golden
goose that he had captured
that is what khilji was doing he was not
doing anything for the people of india
he was oppressing the people of india
right
so he resisted the mongols these
half-hearted small scale
mongol incursions to protect his
investment and to ensure that he
remained
rich and that he remained a king now is
it true for shivaji and other people
i am sorry i completely disagree shivaji
did whatever he did for
for for the people of india so there is
something called
leadership what is leadership leadership
is
service of a limited number of people
it is called service of a constituency
you need to know specifically
who your constituency is and you serve
only those people you don't serve the
whole world
leadership is about serving a small
number of people or a limited number of
people
and the people shivaji served were the
people of india he
re-established hindu swaraj over india
he
freed he liberated india most of india
much of india
from the foreign occupiers and after his
demise his pre his descendants
or his successors went even further and
at its greatest extent the maratha
empire went all the way from
parts of southern india all the way into
parts of afghanistan
and it liberated india from the turks
from the turco mongols the so-called
mughals so they did not do it
i mean there is no record in history
of the marathas extracting wealth from
the indian people
they were not exploitative in any way
whatsoever
right they did uh launch raiding parties
and
loot cities like surat for example but
surat was under the
the mughals at the time and they did not
loot the population
the common people of surah they looked
at the merchants
and those were the benefactors of the
mughals and the mughal
treasury and so that's what the
uh marathas did whatever they did was to
liberate the country and the
people from the outsiders from the from
the occupiers from the oppressors
and the same goes from lakshmi for
lakshmi lakshmibaya was the queen
of jhansi her job was to serve the
people of jhansi
and that's what she did if she had
become the queen eventually of a larger
region
she would have served them too but as
the queen of jhansi it was her duty to
serve the people of chancy
and that's what she died that's what she
did
until her dry dying breath so one has to
look at things in the correct
perspective leadership
is about the service of a limited and
specific group of people
if you are the king or queen of a
certain region your primary duty
your primary objective is to ensure the
long-term security and prosperity
once you become the king or queen of a
larger region you will take care of all
of them so shivaji became
eventually the king of grey of great
parts of india of much of india
and his his successors had a much larger
empire and they served
everybody all the indians of that
maratha empire so that is what it is
khilji did it for himself the marathas
did not do it for themselves they did
not enrich themselves at the expense of
the indian people
neither did rana p whoever that is or
lakshmi bhai
so that is the difference
murano asks how do you learn history
simply
and do fact check i'm sorry there's no
simple way of learning history
i wish i could give you two or three
books and tell you read these books and
you will know all history
or read these two or three books and you
will learn everything about indian
history
unfortunately such books don't exist
even the best books have so many
sections that are are just wrong
and so there is no simple way of
learning history
the way i have learned history is over
many many many years i started reading
seriously when i was around seven years
old and i've read so many books
and i've taken bits and pieces of
information from all these books
and eventually it's created this mind
map inside my mind
and i'm now able to see the different
connections between various parts
of various historical eras and various
events across the world they're all
actually cohesive into one single hole
everything affects each other
nothing is separate so it takes a great
deal of time of lead raw i've read lots
of books
thousands of articles research papers
journal articles and whatnot i've read
even the books that i hate
just to get an idea of what the of what
these uh
incorrect portrayals of history are like
so i am sorry i wish i could i could
give you a very simple way of
learning history unfortunately there is
none maybe i'll have to write some books
myself
and maybe that may be something i'll do
in the future but as of
today there is unfortunately i regret to
say there is no simple way of
of learning history how do you do fact
check okay let's say you have
you have come across some some some
claim
in some narrative of history how do you
fact check that that's a very good
question
you have to look it up from different
perspectives you have to read as much as
you can
about that particular claim from
different angles
read it from western historians read it
from indian historians read it from
from from magazines or journals you know
our leftist
read it from see what the non-leftists
have to say about it
so read as much as you can about it and
then use your intelligence
to sift through all this data and come
come to what you believe
or what your intelligence tells you is
the truth
about this particular episode of history
that is the
methodology that i use i read as much as
i can about
something from all perspectives from
left right non-left
east to west all perspectives what
people have written about it 100 years
ago what people are writing about it
today
and then i try to come to the most
logically
uh sensible conclusion that my
understanding or intellect would allow
me to reach out so that's how i do it
that's how i do fact checking
that's a good question okay let's find
some more questions
thank you to everyone who is
contributing super chats i appreciate it
thank you nick thank you very much
okay this is by ayush my views on
schrodinger's
cat theory it's not a theory it's a
redankan experiment or
thought experiment so it serves to
illustrate
one of the one of the interesting uh
features of quantum mechanics which is
the concept of superposition
so a particle a quantum mechanical
particle
so what's a quantum mechanical particle
or system it is something that exists
at the ultra microscopic molecular
atomic and subatomic
levels of reality so what we see around
us
is the macroscopic view of the world
we can only see the microscopic view we
cannot see the ultra microscopic
uh world which is molecules and atoms
and protons and neutrons and electrons
and quarks and gluons and all of that
right
so that is the quantum level of reality
so at this level nature believe behaves
in very strange ways it
it uh it behaves in accordance with the
laws of quantum
physics quantum mechanics which are very
non-intuitive
it says that a particle b can be in two
places at once
it can be in two states at once right
so if you have a particle that has
that can be in two states spin up and
spin down
then if it is inside a box and you're
not looking at it unless you measure it
it is in two states at the same time
spin up as well as pin down
it's only when you observe it or make a
measurement that
this superposition of two states
collapses into a single state either
up or down so that is
what quantum superpositions are
so this was a thought experiment done by
one of the
uh i don't know who was the originator
of this was it plank was it
not sure but this was the this was a
humorous
way of of looking at this but also an
instructive way of looking at this
so let's say you have a box in which you
have a cat
and you have a radiation
you have you have a source of of poison
gas
which can be released when a certain
radiation is emitted by
a radiation emitter so you keep the cat
inside the box with his apparatus
and this random radiation release may
happen anytime
so unless you look unless you open the
box and look inside you don't know if
the cat is alive or dead
so as long as you have not observed the
cat
by opening the box the cat is in a
superposition of two states
alive and dead so that serves to
illustrate
one of the superposition principle of
quantum mechanics
so it's not a theory it's a thought
experiment
and there are many more much more
complex
versions of the of this thought
experiment that
actually throw up more paradoxes
so that's in brief about the schrodinger
cat
thought experiment of quantum mechanics
okay let me find some more questions
this is by artist shirish do our height
or size differ in parallel universes for
example
five feet in this universe and seven
feet in another
universe well uh there is no way as of
now as of today to answer this question
because
we don't know if parallel universes
exist firstly
and secondly even if they do exist we
don't know what
the laws of nature are in those
universes because we have no means of
going there
and seeing what what it's like over
there so
anything could be possible according to
the string theory landscape there could
be 10 raised to 500 or more
different kinds of parallel parallel
universes with different laws of physics
so if that is indeed true then anything
goes anything could be possible
five feet in this universe could be
seven feet there or vice versa
or you may have very different laws of
physics that we can't even think of here
so anything's possible but it's all
hypothetical it's not even a theory
it's a hypothesis and as of today we
have no means of either proving it
or falsifying it so it's
well it's all hypothetical as of today i
there is no way we don't have
even one piece of information that could
possibly
answer this question so as of now we
don't know
[Music]
okay let me find some more good
questions
asks what do you think about japan's
history and meiji restoration
also about buddhism and was there anyone
who had gone to japan after him
because we all know about the isolation
policy of the shogun
well that's a lot of questions in one
but see
the meiji restoration was an attempt
by the meiji emperor in the 19th century
to reform japan it was a nationalistic
thing he
uh he revived the industries he
placed a great deal of emphasis on
industrialization on modernization
and he tried to remove buddhism
from japan he he portrayed buddhism as
an intrusive
foreign religion and he tried to ban
buddhism he tried to destroy
buddhist shrines temples monasteries he
tried to convert buddhist monks into
shinto monks etc
he failed the people did not accept this
so buddhism is still very much a part of
japan but today
because of the meiji uh reformation and
what he tried
at least today there is this perception
among the japanese people
that buddhism and shinto are separate
religions earlier it was the same thing
it had syncretized beautifully today
they are considered to be separate
religions
and buddhism is now regarded as a
religion that is indian in origin or
foreign in origin
it is not regarded as a japanese
religion but it is still very much part
of the japanese lifestyle and the life
and the rituals and traditions
so that's what he the meiji emperor
tried to do
uh i'm not sure who bodhisina is i know
bodhidharma
was there anyone who went to japan after
him so indian monks did not really go to
japan
all of this influence of buddhism and
hinduism and indian culture and
traditions
that came into japan came by china so
china became the storehouse and
repository
and propagator of indian culture in
various directions
and it is china it is chinese monks and
chinese influences
that passed this on and transmitted all
of this
rich indian culture into japan so that's
what happened indian
monks never went to japan all this all
those years ago
so this transmission of buddhism and
hinduism and indian
culture and traditions into japan
happened at least
1500 years before today at least and
this all happened via china
it is indian monks and teachers and
scholars and gurus and translators
and other people who went to china and
dharmicized china introduced hinduism
and buddhism into china
but they did not go further east from
china it is chinese
monks and other individuals who went
into japan
and indianized japan
what about the isolation policy of the
shogun that happened much later
that's in the past thousand years or so
japanese history is also
a history of many ups and downs so you
had the shogunate period you had the
uh samurai who were in power for a long
time you are the shoguns these warlords
so they're very isolationists to a great
extent
and that is the legacy of isolationism
that was there in japan for a long time
and it is the meiji emperor who
who decided to undo all that to open up
japan to western influences especially
and to turn japan into a powerful
economy
and that had a lot of uh downstream
repercussions eventually which would
lead to
the military is the great militarization
of japan which we saw about 100
or so 120 30 years ago so japan became
an imperial power of military power
uh and it eventually led to
its role in world war ii so that's in
brief about
this interesting question good question
okay let's find some more questions
can indian subcontinent including tibet
and southeast asian nations
reunite to form greater india at least
how the european union works
is it possible how will it happen see
right now the indian subcontinent is
divided on the lines of religion
so anytime soon it's not going to happen
some people have asked should we
forcibly reintegrate pakistan and other
countries bangladesh with india
if the culture is so different how are
they going to reunite
they are the same people as us us
ethnically they look like us
they have the same languages but the
culture they
the practice the religion the practice
is very much foreign
and it is very and their mindset is very
much anti-india
and anti-hindus and anti-dharmic so it
is very difficult to integrate them
in the in the immediate future maybe we
can
do it gradually over time over the next
100 or so years it's a long
process it won't happen overnight india
did not break up overnight
it was a long process so reintegrating
it will also take a long time
eventually yes i would like to see this
sort of thing happen i don't want india
to reintegrate tibet
and indonesia and all that but we can
have a confederation of like-minded
nations
like the european union with no borders
and and
free travel and all that if the culture
and worldview and attitude is similar
you can't have open borders with a
nationality
or a culture that is very different from
yours and which
essentially is antagonistic to you
so immediately it is not going to happen
in the long run
if india regains its primacy in the
world
if india becomes a strong economic power
a strong cultural civilizational power
then everybody will automatically be
drawn back to india
they will want to reintegrate in some
way or the other with india
and then such a thing can happen so for
this eventuality to become
to become a reality india will have to
first work on itself
work on uplifting itself becoming one of
this one of the primary
powers not just militarily and
economically but culturally and
civilizationally again
if india achieves that then certainly
this can very much
happen so it's a very interesting
question
good question
okay
parikshith asks uh can you share some
light on the taxation system in india
or in the world in ancient times there
were many different forms of taxation
and all that
i am not an economist so i have not
studied this in great detail
but i can tell you where you can find
information about this
in the arthashastra of chanakya so this
text is now available for a very long
time it was not available anywhere
but nowadays you can find this text
available even in online
retailers if you go to your favorite
online retail store
you can order this book in english
translation of it and you can
get a good idea of what the taxation
system was like
because vishnu google goes into all of
these matters in
great detail on what sort of taxation to
employ
what are the rules for taxation and and
what not so that's
a very good source to get a proper
amount of
proper kind of information uh the the
kind of information that you're seeking
in the ancient world you had different
forms of taxation you had
feudal systems in which there was
extortionate taxation
taxation is basically something that's
part of life it's always been part of
almost every culture or civilization and
they have all had different ways of
doing it
so so if you want to know more about the
indian taxation system in detail
in great detail look up the arthashastra
you may even find it online
you may even find the text online so
please look that up
okay let me see some more questions
this is a super sticker by raking khan
thank you so much sir appreciate it
this is a super sticker by one foot wild
thank you very much
thank you i appreciate your contribution
this is a question by prakhar what are
my views about the denisovans and the
mahabharat
so the dennis servants are an
archaic subspecies of humans
who lived many thousand years ago it is
definitely
before the i
i believe that it is most likely to be
much before the era of the mahabharata
or the vedic times
i am not exactly sure how old the
denisovans
were at least 30 40 000 years ago or
much more than that i
i don't recall right now you can look it
up so so that's the thing right so i
don't think there's any
real connection between the denisovans
and the mahabharata there was a question
earlier about the neanderthals
and the ramayana so these are
interesting questions and
because we have so little evidence from
those time periods
so we can't really answer the questions
but as far as the denisovans go
i doubt personally if there is much of a
connection between
them and the mahabharat era
we know that the denisovan people did
not die out their descendants are still
very much alive in eastern asia
in polynesia in other places there may
be even some very small amount of
denison dna in india
possibly indian dna is very
very poorly understood we only have
because there is not much research done
in india because we don't have any
high quality genetics research
institutes apart from one or two
like verbal sahani etc but there's a
great deal more to
discover about indian genetics so maybe
there is
some fragmentary ancestry of the
denisovans among
us but i don't think that there is any
connection between the denisovans and
the mahabharat
all right
aryan sharma asks about uttarakhand
history well uttarakhand is such a small
region it's a very beautiful region
and it's got a very interesting
mix and blend of cultures so
i as of now i don't really have an
answer
i i know you've been asking this
question many times as of now i really
don't know much about
i don't know much about the history of
this very specific small region of india
but i will look it up and i will get
back to you about this because it's a
very interesting part of
part of our country small region in the
north
i see history from a larger perspective
i see it from a cultural civilizational
perspective i like to see history
i like to see the cause and effect
change the causality change
and what happens when some an event
far away eventually affects you in what
ways does it affect you
so that's the approach towards history
that i've had it's a large picture
approach
i tend to see from century to century
from civilization to civilization
so this specific small region of india
has thus far
eluded my attention but i will look into
it and maybe
in the future i will answer this
question so thank you for this question
anurag asks can india ever match with
usa china in
in terms of quantum supremacy and how
can we commercialize
it so i would say that india in the in
terms of
artificial intelligence machine learning
and quantum computing is at least 10
years behind
the us and china in the u.s in china
they have developed this
academic military industrial
complex in which all three of these
these disparate branches help each other
right
and that's why there is so much emphasis
on research in the academic system
in the us and china the chinese have
basically emulated
the american system and they are now
trying to surpass it
if you look at india's academic system
there is no
emphasis on research it's all teaching
from textbooks that somebody else has
written
so india lags behind very badly in in
research and development
in these fields ai quantum mecha
quantum computing i don't think anyone's
even tried to build a quantum
computer in india thus far can
india match up in the future india can
if we if we
invest in these technologies if we build
research centers
if we put the best minds to work we
we don't have any shortage of best minds
we have the best minds in the world
which we export
in the millions to other countries right
so if we leverage our innate inborn
intelligence and brilliance and if we
set up these
research centers and if we fund them
properly
we can at least i would say reach the
level of the us in china
in the next 10 to 15 to 20 years
definitely and if we can reach that
level we can certainly
surpass them but it would take
some initiative from the government for
this to happen
or from the private sector but the
private sector is constrained
in many ways the private sector is all
about
profits if you can't generate a profit
then you will you will go out of
business
and in india what is profitable is not
this sort of thing as of now today
so the government will have to take some
initiative and as of now it's not
happened i hope
i mean something was announced a year or
two ago that
10 million or so dollars would be spent
on this which is
a paltry amount of money we need to
spend billions of dollars
in order to make this happen and some
may look upon this
as a wasteful investment when india
still has poor people
but hey this is going to pay you back a
million times fold in the future
so it is a worthwhile investment it is
always worthwhile
to invest in science and technology even
if
you don't see the immediate outcome or
fruits of this investment
the fruits are the are going to be
visible in the long run
for example if we had not built isro 40
50 years ago
then we would not have any rocket
technology we would not be able to
launch our own satellites
and we would be dependent on other
countries so that investment in rocket
science which looked ludicrous in the
1950s and 60s and 70s
has paid back so much to us today so
that is the view we need to have that's
the approach we need to have
we need to think long term so india does
need to invest a great deal
in artificial intelligence machine
learning and associated technologies
like
quantum computing
okay some more questions
okay pradyum asks why can't we just
go attack europe and bring back
everything that belongs to us gold and
diamonds
or any other nation which looted us
about 45 trillion
so yeah the total figure is estimated to
be around 45 trillion dollars
worth of money today what was extracted
out of india today
that's around at least three times the
entire gdp of the uk
the thing is this you see uh the money
was basically taken out of india by the
by the english by the british but that
money was reinvested the treasure was
reinvested
in other places it built up the entire
country
right the uk the so-called uk and it was
redistributed to different places
different families
across europe across the americas as
well so that wealth that was stolen from
india is not
present only in the uk today or only
present in one location it's spread
across the western world
the entire upsurge the resurgence the
so-called
renaissance of the western world was
powered to a great extent was fueled
with
indian treasure indian indian money the
entire scientific and industrial
revolution that happened
in in britain was fueled by indian money
so what can we do can we just go and
loot it all back
i mean where do we find that gold it's
no longer in the original form
where are all those diamonds they've
been broken up they've been sold they've
been reinvested
that money has been recycled many many
many times over
all that treasure is is it's it's
present in the form of real estate and
buildings and
militaries and in economies so how do we
get it back there's no way of getting
back
and secondly do we even have the
military power and strength
to go and wage war against the whole of
europe how much money does it take to
sustain a military campaign
an extended military campaign will it
let's do a cost-benefit analysis we'll
have to spend billions or maybe
trillions of dollars worth of money
in order to launch such a massive
military campaign do we have the
military strength for that do have we
invested enough in the
air force the navy the army we haven't
thus far
so we are in no position to do that even
if we were to build up such a strong
military
is it worth the investment can't we use
just use that money to build our own
economy
and rebuild it to a greater extent than
what it was before
so these are the questions we have to
ask ourselves it's all about doing a
cost benefit analysis
yes this is injustice they stole our
wealth they
enriched themselves at our expense they
built up the entire so-called western
civilization
uh based upon india's stolen wealth
the majority of the loot was from india
so this is a historical injustice now
what do we do about it
the best way to repay them for what
they've done to us
is to make ourselves strong and
prosperous again
that's the in my opinion that's the best
way to to do that that's the best answer
we will rise again we'll get stronger
again we will rise above everybody else
again
we'll get a strong economy strong great
uh
quality of life great living standards
and a powerful military which will
safeguard what we are building up and
then we look to the future we
look into space exploration and other
technologies and we expand outwards
so i think that is the best revenge so
to say
to those who have done so much injustice
to us i think it is uh
it would be counterproductive uh to go
and attack europe and try to
uh get back what was stolen from from us
so i think that's that's my perspective
about this particular
issue okay i will take two more
questions
and then we will be done for today uh
okay let me take a couple of
good questions
what are my views in mahatma gandhi i
will go into that later
who owns mars as of now no one owns mars
but in the future
mars will become privatized if elon musk
jeff bezos
they reach their before the countries
when china the united states
reach mars they may eventually declare a
separate independent
sovereign state there who knows anything
can happen in the future it's all the
future is up for grabs
when it comes to the topic of space
exploration
can the quantum field theory be
associated with the rebirth concept if
so can the to and fro mechanism
of our souls nourish the greater
conscious and
in return refine the next birth
see it's like this quantum field theory
is a scientific theory
rebirth is in the realm of philosophy
and spirituality
these are separate things a theory in
science
is not necessarily going to be
applicable to philosophy
or spirituality what is the difference
between science in philosophy
science deals with the physical
world with the observable world the
world we can see
and touch and observe and perform
experiments upon
that is the limited scope
of science philosophy also concerns
itself with the observable world
but it also concerns itself with with
imaginary or non-observable
uh phenomena or or objects such as the
soul
the consciousness uh ethics and morality
so these things are non-scientific
because science is only about the
physical world
philosophy is greater than science
science is a subset of philosophy
science emerged out of philosophy but
philosophy
transcends science so when you talk
about the soul
reincarnation rebirth well we have no
physical undeniable evidence of this and
therefore this doesn't fall
in the realm of science so how do we
associate quantum field theory with
rebirth
well as far as i understand with the
knowledge that we have today
we cannot associate these two concepts
there
seem to be some connections between
ancient indian philosophy
and quantum physics there seem to be
some connections
but those are all hypothetical as of now
there is a reason why
quantum physicists theoretical
physicists are invariably drawn towards
indian philosophy
because it looks like indian philosophy
can inspire you into getting
into going in the right directions or
maybe it can inspire you
by giving you some possible answers
but there is no direct one-to-one
connection
between the two as we know today
so can quantum field theory be
associated with rebirth concept well
i i don't know i can't answer the
question because these are two different
questions
philosophy and science are separate
spirituality and science
are separate so my answer is i don't
know we have no means of
answering the question we don't know for
sure
with proof that rebirth actually happens
there are many stories
there are many claims but how can you
prove
this for sure right so that's the
question
from a scientific perspective you cannot
prove or disprove
rebirth and reincarnation and therefore
this is not
a theory or concept that belongs inside
science it belongs inside
spirituality and philosophy so that's
the answer to this question
in brief i'll take one more and then we
shall be done
okay um the theory which says that
universe is a simulation
elon musk believes in it see if a famous
person believes in something it doesn't
mean it's true
but my view is that it is a possibility
so today i mean about 20 years ago you
had the playstation 2 which was a very
rudimentary kind of instrument
and the graphics were not that great
today you have the playstation 5
which has much much improved graphics
and it is essentially a small super
computer
so if you have a powerful enough
computer you can actually
simulate an entire universe inside it
with the all the laws of physics with
all the
various components that the universe
possesses and you can create a universe
which evolves within the supercomputer
and if any intelligent life evolves in
the universe it will be
inside the simulation that is created by
our supercomputer
so is it possible that we are also
inside a simulation which is being run
by an enormous
hyper computer somewhere out there it is
possible
it is definitely a possibility so i
think yeah it's a possibility
you cannot you cannot dismiss this
theory it is a valid
theory but we have no proof of it thus
far
so i would say that yes elon musk is
right we may
possibly perhaps be living in
a simulation
all right let me see one more question
last one
and then we shall be done apologize to
everybody whose questions i was not able
to take
i will keep on doing this and we will
have more
okay this is the last question this is
by rohit raina
question two questions the history of
the kashmiri pundits and their genetics
are they related to ancient aryans my
thoughts on ashoka's
nine secret men the history of the
kashmiri pundits is the history of india
their genetics i mean every region has
some specific genetic
peculiarities and all the people of
kashmir are very much related to the
other parts
the people of the other parts of india
what are the aryans the aryans
it's a hypothetical imaginary race there
is no aryan race
if there is any ethnicity which should
be called the aryans it is the indians
and the iranians
nobody else is aryans the europeans are
not aryans
the word arya comes from sanskrit it is
also present
present in ancient persian which is a
derivative
of vedic sanskrit so the aryans are us
we are the aryans
if any race is to be called the aryans
it is us the indians
so are the kashmiri pandits and the
genetics related to the ancient aryans
well you are indians i mean kashmiri
pundits are indians
so we are all the same ethnicity the
people of gujarat will be slightly
genetically different from the people of
bengal
the people of bengal will be slightly
very tiny amount of genetic difference
from tamil nadu and the same from
kashmir and same from from afghanistan
balochistan etc
but overall it's the same ethnicity so
that
is the history of the genetics of the
kashmiris the kashmiri pundits
are actually the kashmiri hindus their
history is as
as old as the history of the indian
subcontinent right
kashmir is known to have existed as and
as
the name kashmir was attested
at least as far back as around 2000
years ago during kanishka's time because
it is known that he
organized one of the great buddhist
conferences
in kashmir in which people with these
scholars from all across the civilized
world came
and participated so the name this the
name of this religion is kashmir is at
least
two thousand years old if not many many
more thousands of years before that
so we are all a very ancient people so
are the kashmiri hindus
they are the ancient aryans so is
everybody else in india
there are no other aryans except for the
indo-iranians the germans aren't aryans
the europeans aren't aryans that's a
that's a word they stole
from sanskrit so it's a sanskrit word
and if any ethnicity is to be called
aryans
it is the indians and the iranians which
includes afghan pakistanis bangladeshis
so on my thoughts on ashoka's secret
nine men well we don't know
it's a secret society if it exists it
will not make itself known
it will not be known to us it will not
be known to historians
the very purpose of having a secret
society is to keep it secret and to keep
it unknown
so maybe it is a myth maybe it is
something a story that somebody make it
made up
maybe it is reality maybe it is not just
nine men or
maybe it's nine men and women maybe it's
not even ashoka who did this or maybe
it's somebody else
some other emperor from before the
answer is we don't know
because it is supposed to be secret
right so that's my answer my friends
it's been a great session thank you all
for participating
we will keep doing this once a week
complete live session
and uh that's it for today i will see
you in tomorrow's session which is going
to be very interesting again
so thank you again everyone for
participating and i will see you
in tomorrow's next episode have a good
night have a good day
bye